<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royal and other innocent bloud crying aloud to heaven for due vengeance. Humbly represented to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament. And with all humble dutifull submission dedicated to the two high and mighty princes, James Duke of York and Henry Duke of Gloucester, his sacred Majestyes Royal brethren. By George Starkey, a true honourer and faithfull friend of his country.</title>
            <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1032_7</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872699</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1032[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Royal and other innocent bloud crying aloud to heaven for due vengeance. Humbly represented to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament. And with all humble dutifull submission dedicated to the two high and mighty princes, James Duke of York and Henry Duke of Gloucester, his sacred Majestyes Royal brethren. By George Starkey, a true honourer and faithfull friend of his country.</title>
                  <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. Warren for Daniel White at the sign of the Seven-stars in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Presenting his enthusiastic support of the Restoration and indicating his enthusiastic royalistic sympathies, and urging retaliation on the Puritan party.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royalists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ROYAL AND OTHER INNOCENT BLOUD CRYING ALOUD TO HEAVEN for due vengeance. Humbly repreſented to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament. <hi>And with all humble dutifull ſubmiſſion dedicated to the two High and Mighty Princes, James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> his Sacred Majeſtyes ROYAL BRETHREN.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Starkey,</hi> A true honourer and faithfull friend of his Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui non prohibet, quod in ſuâ poteſtate eſt, jubet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Warren</hi> for <hi>Daniel White</hi> at the Sign of the Seven-ſtars in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168902:2"/>
            <head>To the High and Mighty Princes, <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> his Sacred Majeſtyes happy, and high born Brethren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Illustrious Princes, this ſhort tractate, though far unworthy your ſight, much leſs your Princely Patronage, yet is humbly dedicated to your gracious, and Royall hands, and ſubmitted to your moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious cenſure; firſt conſidering your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent goodneſs, by which you can (with your favour) make that which is of no worth, valuable upon the ſcore of your Princely
<pb facs="tcp:168902:3"/>acceptance: ſecondly becauſe it is humbly preſented to the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, of the firſt of which, you are incomparable members; laſtly conſidering the ſubject it treats of, and the intended ſcope of it, on which ſcore, I hope it may meet with a kind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance from your true filiall Piety and Princely wiſdom: Pardon moſt royall Heroes, this bold preſumption of him, who wants deſerts, yet preſuming on your gracious pardon, hath the boldneſs, (may it not be interpreted impudence) to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>High and Mighty Princes,</salute>
               <signed> Your Royall Highneſſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant, and moſt humble Orator. GEORGE STARKEY.</signed>
               <dateline>St. Thomas Apoſtles
<date>June. 18. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168902:3"/>
            <head>MOST HONOURABLE LORDS AND WORTHY GENTLEMEN.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od having been pleaſed ſo highly to honour you, and by your meanes thus far to make theſe Nations happy, as to reſtore unto us our long exiled, moſt excellently accompliſhed King, and us to him, it behoves every true ſubject, with thankfulneſs to addreſſe himſelf to him by prayer, that he would abundantly bleſſe him unto us, and amongſt us, by pouting out upon him his ſpirit; inriching him with all ſpirituall and temporall good things, and to neglect this duty is, and will doubtleſſe be accounted their ſin, who are guilty thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This remarkable bleſſing of God vouchſafed to the whole Nation, and ſo ſignall Character of his good will towards you, (whom he hath at laſt choſen ſo far to go on in this work, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving often before th own aſide ſeverall perſons, who have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted it, not only unſucceſsfully, but with the loſſe of their lives; nor hath hitherto ſuffered any forcible oppoſition, to retard, much leſſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaten the overthrow of ſuch happy beginnings;)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168902:4"/>ought to ſtir up both your, and all our hearts, to acknowledg with thankfulneſs theſe his favors, ſo great, that we ſcarce durſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly put up our requeſts for them, and ſo unexpected, that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdom could hardly believe, much leſs dictate meanes to effect, what God in his bleſſed providence hath wonderfully brought about, beyond both our deſerts and hopes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſerious conſideration whereof, hath invited, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with me, in few words to begge, and intreat of you, that as God hath ſo far honoured you in the ſight of theſe Nations, you would make his divine Majeſty ſuch Chriſtian returnes of gratitude, as may Evidence, and ſeal your ſincerity, and true piety to this and future ages.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the thoughts, how God hath choſen you, as a ſelect number out of, and before many thouſand Engliſhmen, to bring home to them (as I may ſay) a moſt heart-refreſhing return of many prayers, and teares, which for about twenty yeares, in the midſt of diſtracting calamities, have been poured out before, and addreſſed to the Divine Majeſty, by ſuch who have an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the throne of grace, may now ingage you henceforth to deny God nothing, which from his word of truth may appear to be expected, and required of you, as a gratefull teſtimony, of your true Chriſtian obedience, and thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It hath ſeemed good to the Divine providence, which we may truly call wonderfull, ſo to over-rule of late, the counſels of our former oppreſſors, (who by ſtrange ſucceſs, and almoſt incredible dexterity in villany, had almoſt involved both our Church and ſtate in unavoidable ruine; grinding without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, theſe (once free) but at length wofully enthralled Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, faſtning on their neck, an Iron, uneaſy yoak of ſervitude, making them (with <hi>Samſon</hi>) baſely to grind, and abide capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and curbing them with rigor, who before repined at, grew weary of, and rejected the milder ſcepter, and ſo to enſnare them in their contrivances, that their plots (like potters veſſells) were broken upon the wheele, nor produced any thing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſtraction to themſelves, together with unſetledneſs in the Nation, whence aroſe diſcontent, loſs of trade, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and by means of the laſt of theſe, the waſted peoples whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168902:4"/>murmurings, and repinings on all hands were ſo many and urgent, that the Maſter builders of our new <hi>Babel,</hi> by their own jealouſies, miſunderſtandings, and animoſities, were in ſhort time diſperſed hither and hither, through the good hand of God, without ſtroke on either ſide.</p>
            <p n="6">6. What height of fury, and deſperate reſolution was on their ſide, God knew, and took notice of, nor was it unknown to moſt of thoſe, who deſired, and prayed for ſuch a compoſure, and ſettlement of affaires, as we now ſee, through his great goodneſs, and undeſerved kindneſs to us, who conſidering the preparations and contrivances to hinder what we now happily injoy, could not expect this redemption, but as a purchaſs, and with the loſs of the lives of thouſands, the ſhedding much bloud, and expoſing our hopes to extream hazard. The oppreſſed City, and groaning Countryes were reſolved, either to ſhake off the Arbitrary yoak of Uſurpation and Tyranny, or to periſh in the attempt. On the other hand the fatall cauſers of our long paſt and preſent calamities, animated with guilt and deſpair, were reſolved either to make good their ground, or expire like <hi>Cateline,</hi> that is, ſell their life as dear as poſſible, and cover the place, they maintained fighting in life, with their breathleſs Carkaſes after death, or like <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mry,</hi> rather than loſe (by ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) their power and eſtates, fire the whole Nation firſt, then ſet ſome Cityes, and Caſtles on flame over their heads, and periſh together.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Yet it pleaſed the Lord of hoaſts, to diſſipate their armed powers, fruſtrate their deſignes, and leave the Ringleaders, ſtript of all ſuccour, to the ſcourge of juſtice. It ſtood with his honour and wiſdom, to reſtrain the rage and fury of man; to glorifye himſelf, by delivering up theſe great <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> oppreſſors, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting <hi>Moabites, Philiſtim</hi> Lords, (with their <hi>Balaam</hi> like Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Southſayers) without ſo much as drawing Sword, or firing Piſtoll in a hoſſile way; notwithſtanding, they incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged each other, and complotted, as well by hidden machinations, as open hoſtility, to prevent our ſettlement, and ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from juſtice.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This miraculous language of Gods actions, ſpeaking as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168902:5"/>his power and wiſdom, ſo his great love to us, gives me hopes, and in a manner aſſurance, that you, by whom theſe unlikely changes were brought about, ſo much to Gods glory, and the Kingdomes hope of happineſs, will not look upon (with ſcorne) or reject with (contempt) any humble advice, which is ſincerely offered, and tendred to your honours wiſdom, and moſt judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration, by one, who moſt cordially, and unfeignedly honours you, as well for your actions, as worth: however in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, or unworthy, to ſuggeſt any thing (by way of Counſell) he may juſtly appear unto you.</p>
            <p n="9">9. God, who hath made choice of your Honours, out of ſo great a Kingdom, wherein are found ſo many, and eminent men, able both for parts and piety, to appoint you the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of ſuch happy tidings, or Angells of peace, unto theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, having laid aſide before, ſo many, and often, both perſons of remarke, and who zealouſly endeavoured the effecting (had God ſeen it good) of what is now proſperouſly brought to paſs in your hand, whereby in his providence he ſpake plainly, that neither was that the ſeaſon, nor thoſe the perſons, by whom he intended deliverance to this his people, therefore they either failed, or were unſucceſsfully ruined in their pious undertakings. The ſame thing God then ſaw good to deny them, he hath made eaſy to you, levelling (as it were) mountaines before you, ſo that you (worthy Patriots) are become our <hi>Zorobabels,</hi> to redeem and reſtore our captivity, to repair our breaches, to ſettle again upon its true and antient Baſis, theſe three great, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſadly broken Kingdomes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Remember I beſeech you that God, who both names, and appoints honours, and makes proſperous his Inſtruments, who called his anoynted <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and made gates of braſs fly open before him, and who knowes, but perhaps the ſame God, who hath rayſed you, beyond what either you could expect, or find meanes (of your ſelves,) to compaſs, who hath made you ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable to both King and Country, ſo far as to deſerve all the honour poſſible, for this age to invent, thereby to celebrate your name and worth to poſterity, hath likewiſe by his providence ſtirred me up, to ſpeak a word to your wiſdomes in ſeaſon, my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168902:5"/>diſpoſition and propenſity being (I dare aſſure your honours) to have kept private, and aſſiſted you (to my power) only with my moſt ſincere wellwiſhes and prayers to God, put up in your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Howbeit, conſidering the ſeaſon, I am in a manner compelled to come forth as I do, thus publickly, to offer my moſt ſerious thoughts, and reflections of ſpirit upon the late miraculous tranſactions wrought, by the divine providence, among us; to your moſt grave and judicious thoughts, with humble ſubmiſſion, to your moſt diſcreet cenſure.</p>
            <p n="12">12. A ſeaſon, wherein Gods mercies are plentifully poured out upon us, notwithſtanding our great unworthineſs, wherein he is moſt ſignally propitious, affording opportunity to make up all our breaches, to repair what hath been thrown down and defaced; happy therefore may he be accounted, who ſhall any way aſſiſt towards a firm, laſting eſtabliſhment, and well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſettlement.</p>
            <p n="13">13. A ſeaſon, wherein many broken bones need binding up, many diſlocated joynts ſetling in place, many ulcers ſearching, and cleanſing, and (truſt me, moſt honourable Lords, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentlemen,) many rotten pieces of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh cutting off, many deſperate humours lancing, much dead and proud fleſh to be taken away by corroſives, if ever a ſound cure be expected, or hoped for in this body politick.</p>
            <p n="14">14. What your proceedings have been in order hereunto; we have ſeen, and have all cauſe both to bleſs God, and honour you, for ſo much as already we have found effected: what your further intentions are, ſeverall of your late votes, gives us both grounds to gueſs and hope. Give leave therefore, right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and moſt deſerving Patriots, to tender modeſtly, to your mature deliberation, ſome obſervations, which I have made, comparing your determinations, and reſolves, with the apparent occurrences, and (to my apprehenſion,) very plain language, and lowd expreſſions of theſe late Divine providences.</p>
            <p n="15">15. God, whoſe judgments are unfathomable, and wayes unſearchable, ſaw good to bring upon there Nations (for many yeares paſt) ſuch flouds of calamities, as were ſcarce known,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168902:6"/>or heard of before, in this, or any neighbouring Nation; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Hiſtories, as well as humane memory, being at a <hi>non-plus</hi> to produce the like inſtances.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Nor were theſe our miſeries more deplorable, our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities grievous, and inſufferable, than the wayes, and meanes whereby we became involved in them, abominable, horrible, ex ecrable, deteſtable, and damnable.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Quinteſſence of Rebellion, and Treachery, was ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated by moſt palpable, amazing perjury, falſhood, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull dealing, was exerciſed on all occaſions, toward all rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by our inſlaving taskmaſters, whoſe breach of oaths, and renouncing their Loyall Allegiance to the King, ſerved but for a Prologue, to a large following Tragedy, wherein, O! the perfidious practiſes, acted by them againſt the Parliament, which they at pleaſure diſmembred, (caſhiering one houſe) and garbled, (ſecluding out of the other houſe) all ſuch who ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or hated to be like themſelves; and having thus tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med two houſes of <hi>Englands</hi> Parliament, into a <hi>Mock junto;</hi> (called afterwards in deriſion, the Rump, which was the by-word at laſt of every idle Ballad-maker) even, this creature of their own, was by them made a <hi>Mock Pageant,</hi> uſed for a ſtalking horſe, (ſometimes) otherwhiles thrown aſide at pleaſure, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi hſtanding many moſt facred vowes to the contrary, not more ſolemnely made than broken, and almoſt as ſoon. One while they ſet up an Uſurping Protector, (who would not be ſo dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied withall,) however his Sonne, to whom they were likewiſe bound by voluntary proteſtations, engagements, and addreſſes, quickly had experience of their Inconſtancy, and Treacherous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. In a word <hi>England</hi> hath been ever ſince her rebellion againſt, and Apoſtacy from lawfull Authority; all along made a Scene, of moſt groſs perjury, and ſhamefull Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery:</p>
            <p n="18">18. Nor was this all, but as if <hi>Satan</hi> had taken poſſeſſion of the Nation, and held it as his own private murthers (which were frequent and mercileſs,) were ſwallowed up in that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation the Murther of his Sacred Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: Athieſticall profaneſs, ſacriledg, and ſeditious hereſy,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168902:6"/>went (hand in hand) with the (almoſt) extirpation, of all our fundamentall Lawes; So that civill liberty, and true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, were in hazard, (almoſt quite loſt) together, inſteed of which were brought in, Arbitrary tyranny, and ruling by will and luſt, (in the ſtate) ſcandalous in piety, irreligious Sects, and blaſphemous hereſyes (in the Church; theſe with an Impudent brow, defied (I may ſay) heaven it ſelf. In a word, if ſuperlative villany in practiſe, exemplary malice in contrivance, or reſolute impenitency in perſeverance, if helliſh deſignes, implacable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and incorrigible obſtinacy, may be an aggravation of their crimes, who in theſe yeares paſt, of the Kingdomes calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have been publick offendors, and cauſed, promoted, or helpt to perpetuate them, (had they been able to effect it,) certainly there lies on them as much guilt, as <hi>Satan</hi> could furniſh them with; or their own reprobate natures contract.</p>
            <p n="19">19. But God hath been mercifull unto theſe poor bleeding Kingdomes, ſo far, as to defeat at length their plots, who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing of will, to render us compleatly, perpetually, and irrecoverably miſerable, they wanted not mallice, in which they were in placable, and inveterate, nor induſtry, wherein indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, nor preparation, for which moſt vigilant, nor deſign, in which they beheld us with ſcorn and triumph, groaning forth our laſt deſpairing ſighs, and lying beyond hope or remedy, under the clawes of their moſt mercileſs rage, but God alone, hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them this unexpected check, to the glory of his goodneſs, and undeſerved grace be it ſpoken, there is nothing left us to boaſt of, who could only ſit down, and groan out our ſighs to him, by reaſon of our oppreſſures and burdens, but neither did nor knew we to help our ſelves in the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="20">20. This Divine diſpoſure of affaires, after ſo wonderfull a manner, ſeemes by way of duty to ſuggeſt unto us two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, how infinitely we ſtand obliged to that good God, who hath been ſo eminently, and unexpectedly gracious unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, what juſtice he now requires and expects, ſhould be done on them whoſe inſolencies, and monſtrous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168902:7"/>cannot be overlooked, unleſs we reſolve, to bring upon our ſelves, and intaile upon our poſterity, ſuch curſes, as may make them abhor the remiſenes and neglect, perhaps, the very memory of their fathers.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The former of theſe, I ſhall touch briefly, and ſo paſs it over, it being far more readily owned, known, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be a duty, than carefully and conſcienciouſly practiſed, which indeed, will be performed, very lamely, and ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, unleſs the latter be more diligently heeded, and ſeriouſly attended.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Let us in the firſt place therefore, all with hearts and hands lifted up to the moſt high, with thankfull prayſes cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate his name, publiſh and make known this his great goodneſs, eſpecially, endeavour the ſpeedy amendment of our lives, the irregularity of which, hath no doubt been the continued cauſe, which provoked God to bring, and ſo long to exerciſe us, with ſo many, ſo great, and perplexing miſeries.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Let us confeſs, bewayle, and humble our ſelves, for our paſt ingratitude, that injoying ſo great, and invaluable pledges, of Divine favour, we made ſo few, and unſutable returnes of them.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Let us repent our undutifullneſs toward ſuperiours, contempt of Authority, ſtudy of change and want of love one towards another, which provoked God to give us up to men of baſe extraction, and worſe principles, and to let ſervants rule over us.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Let us hereafter prize Gods offers of Love to us in his Church, nor loath heavenly <hi>Manna</hi> any more, as we have done, inſtead of which we have for a long time been fed (in the Swines trough) with huskes, not yet fatiſfied therewith. Theſe reflections I hope will be made in our breaſts, and ſuch like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes we ſhall give in remembrance, and acknowledgment, of this undeſerved, unlooked for, yea almoſt miraculous deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</p>
            <p n="26">26. In reference to the ſecond head, I ſhall humbly take leave, to lay open my breaſt, in ſpeaking my conſcience, and diſcover my love, and faithfullneſs to the Nation, in addreſſing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168902:7"/>my ſelf, with all poſſible duty, and reſpect, unto our moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords, add worthy Commons, however a weak, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Orator.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Right honourable, and truly deſerving Patriots, it lies now in your power, and under God is wholly left at your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to make theſe Nations either really, and compleatly, or apparently, and in part only happy, perfectly to cure, or to palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their diſeaſe, to give them totall eaſment; or for a ſhort time to leave them ſound at bottom, or in danger of a relapſe, and breaking out again, with no leſs Anguiſh, perhaps full as much, or more danger to the body than before.</p>
            <p n="28">28. His ſacredly Royall, and moſt gracious Majeſty, hath committed things wholly to your diſpoſe, nor do I cueſtion, but your piety and prudence, will lead you, to reſpect him as Gods deputy here on earth, yearather to look beyond him to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who by his meanes, betruſted you with his power, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs expects the execution thereof, according to his revealed will, as you will anſwer the contrary at your perill, in that great, and dreadfull day of Judgment.</p>
            <p n="29">29. To acquit the guilty, and condemn the Innocent are equally abominable in his preſence, who is the God of Juſtice and truth.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Beſides the murder of his moſt ſacred Majeſty, of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py memory, againſt whoſe life to conſpire, is death without mercy, by the known Lawes of the Land, there have been (fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) committed other horrible, bloudy murthers, the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of which, are every day ſold among us, but far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly kept on record in Gods Book, nor ſooner ſhall the guilt of them be taken off, from a private ſcore on Earth, and not reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but it will forthwith be entred down upon the publick, or Nations ſcore, in the book of the moſt righteous God, who uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally taketh the vengeance thereof into his own hand.</p>
            <p n="31">31. My earneſt prayer to God, in your behalf, is and ſhall be, that you will not involve your ſelves with the Nation, in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, by acquitting the moſt notoriouſly guilty, in that kind, which ever <hi>England</hi> nouriſht, or groan'd under, the ready way to provoke God to revenge it upon the whole Nation, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168902:8"/>the City. What a plague may follow this lenity, if ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed (which the Lord avert) he only knowes, who (perhaps) waits but your finall determination, before he give it fatal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>(Si quid delirant Reges, plectuntur Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vi)</hi> Perhaps the neareſt relations, or deareſt friends may be ſo ſignally ſwept away, from the chiefe authors of theſe crying murtherers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity; As may at once both convince them of ſinfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and pierce their bleeding hearts with ten thouſand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. Pray God I may not prove a Prophet, nor do I ſpeake it, but with deprecation, only faithfullneſs unto you compels me thus to utter my ſelfe, and lay open my breaſt to your Honours and wiſedomes.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Believe it, my Lords and Gentlemen, Seven or ten is not a competent number to be expoſed to juſtice, and thoſe moſt of them fled out of reach, when ſevenſcore at leaſt are over head and eares dipt, and beyond excuſe concerned, in that amazing murder of Majeſty, (as to guilt, in the eye of mans law) though I believe not all alike involved in the unpardonable ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations of knowledg, and malice.</p>
            <p n="33">33. But beſides that abominable murder, ſeverall more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, but as cruell, have been committed on divers perſons both of rank and eſteem, as might be inſtanced, in the Lords <hi>Capell, Hamilton, Holland,</hi> with many Knights and Gentlemen of worth, as <hi>Lucas, Liſle, Hide, Andrewes, Penruddock, Grove, Burleigh, Love, Gerard, Vowell, Buſhell, Hewit, Slingsby Aſhton, Bettely, Stacy,</hi> with others, for whoſe bloud, when the holy and juſt God ſhall make inquiſition, he will find no legall reckoning made. And what muſt poor <hi>England</hi> then expect from him, who hath expreſsly declared, that bloud defiles a land, nor can be purged from its guilt, but by their bloud who ſhed it, who hath therefore commanded, the retaliation of bloud upon the ſhedders head, whether man or beaſt. Yea I tremble to think, when God himſelf ſhall come to take ſatisfaction thereof, what our lot may be, unleſs in the Nations behalf its moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords and Commons by impartiall juſtice prevent this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain judgment, if neglect or default herein be made.</p>
            <p n="34">34. To avoid which guilt, and (if it may be) to keep off judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168902:8"/>like to enſue thereon, give me leave to preſent your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours with ſome few conſiderations, nor I hope unſeaſonable, or tedious, which I ſtudyed to avoid, firſt by brevity, and next, by ſending them forth, and humbly preſenting them to your view, before the act of Indemnity be fully concluded on.</p>
            <p n="35">35. I am ſenſible of the multiplicity of your preſſing affaires, and know, that you have not leiſure from your moſt ſerious debates, and agitations, to attend large declamations, againſt the crying ſinne of bloud, how it ſtaines, and defiles a land; yea, I am confident, ſuch common places are very familiar to you, who are neither unacquainted with the Judgments on that ſcore denounced in holy writ, nor unfurniſhed with inſtances, and examples of Divine vengeance, attending the impunity of that crying ſin, recorded not only by Chriſtian, but profane Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p n="36">36. The conſiderations (then) which I ſhall moſt humbly ſuggeſt, ſhall be ſuch as are taken from, and obvious to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, of thoſe (eſpecially) who have minded the late dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, both of God and man, toward us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And in them my intended ſcope and aime is, partly to find and mark out ſuch whoſe guilt of this nature, is beyond both pardon and excuſe, and whoſe impunity cannot but render the Kingdom very unſafe, if we will believe his threatnings, whoſe judgments, as well as mercies, are wonderfull, and true.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Partly, to preſs the loud calls, and clear motives (appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the divine diſpenſations, and theſe late overtures, and tranſactions) for impartiall juſtice, which to paſs by unregarded, is to provoke God, after once or twiſe, yea reiterated ſpeaking, by his providence, without attention, on mans part, to uſe ſhortly, ſuch language, as may make all our bones tremble.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But laſtly, and moſt eſpecially, to obviate and anſwer ſome plauſible, through carnall (at beſt) if not unſound argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are brought and preſſed, in their behalf; in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of which, if I give way to, or diſcover any private grudg, or paſſion, or appear ſo to your wiſdoms, my heart much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives me, for I have not the leaſt particular diſaffection, for any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168902:9"/>thoſe unfortunately criminall Gentlemen, whom I crave leave to call ſo, though their actions brand them with ſo much barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cruelty, as may bring in queſtion their very humanity, ſo far am I from peſonall prejudice conceived againſt any of their number. And I can ſeriouſly, ſolemnly, and truly appeal to the ſeacher of hearts, that I ſhould much more de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>redly have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt my ſelf in their behalf, and been an urgent, though unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy interceſſor for them, but that my conſcience aſſures me, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, that whoever ſo favours or befriends them, as to procure their indemnity, doth what in him lyes, (ignorantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) to pluck the fierceſt of Gods Judgments upon the heads, of himſelf, and his poſterity, and to involve the Kingdom in ſuch future calamities, as may juſtly render his indiſcreet cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, (rather cruell pity) a cauſe of dolefull lamentation many ages yet to come.</p>
            <p n="37">37. As to thoſe perſons, whoſe pardon cannot conſiſt with the Nations ſafety, unleſs we flatter our ſelves with peace, where God hath moſt expreſsly declared, and ſeverely denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the contrary, it is very worth our enquiry, that in caſe a black cloud of nationall miſeries, ſhould again overſpread the already nigh conſumed, and deſtroyed Kingdomes, (which God in mercy forbid) we may ſpeedily recollect with our ſelves the cauſe, and in time apply a ſuitable remedy.</p>
            <p n="38">38. It was once remarkable, the caſe of Gods people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the time of <hi>David</hi>'s Reign; year after year, one of the foreſt of Gods plagues, afflicted that Nation; three ſucceſſive yeares famine, put <hi>David</hi> upon enquiry after the cauſe; who had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from the Divine oracle, that bloud guiltineſs in the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> who ſlew the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> had called for that nationall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; now becauſe <hi>David,</hi> (who ought not to have let crimes of that nature paſs,) had not revenged it, after he come to the Crown, all <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſmarted ſeverely for this neglect, and yet the Actor was dead, who with his ſonne, fell in battell, and a great ſlaughter was made among the whole Army beſides; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, till particular vengeance for this bloud was taken, and Seven of <hi>Saul</hi>'s family, (among whom were five of <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> ſonnes, the daughter of <hi>Saul,</hi> born to <hi>Adriell</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillai</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168902:9"/>the <hi>Meholathite</hi>) were delivered up to the injured <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and by them hanged before the Lord, the guilt of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, ſtill cryed for vengeance to heaven, and was heard ſo many yeares after, and avenged by the righteous God, with a ſore famine, three yeares together.</p>
            <p n="39">39. My prayer is that the like lot befall not <hi>England,</hi> which is much more to be feared, conſidering the quality of the perſons murthered among us, not <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> who were part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by God devoted to deſtruction, and ſaved their lives by a falſe feigned meſſage, deluding the two credulous Princes, and bringing them to a raſh unadviſed oath, to ſpare their lives; who yet condemned them to perpetuall drudgery to the whole congregation, but our King here was butchered, our Lords, Knights, Gentry, Godly Divines, and eminent Citizens, ſlaughtered. Thoſe were ſlain by a King in appearing zeal, who might have for colour of this action. Firſt, the change of Government. Secondly, the fraud, by which that Oath of the Princes of the congregation, was deceitfully obtained. Thirdly, that the perſons ſwearing, and ſworn to, were long ſince dead, nor could a grant (fraudulently procured) bind poſterity. Fourthly, that Gods command was to extirpate them, without mercy or pity. Fifthly, the diſpleaſure of him manifeſted againſt <hi>Iſraell,</hi> for ſparing, and making Leagues with ſuch Nations, which he had devoted to deſtruction, and commanded their utter rooting out. Sixthly, the Divine anger againſt himſelf, becauſe he had been diſobediently pitifull in ſparing the King of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck,</hi> with part of the ſpoile. Seventhly, that though the Princes of the congregation had ſpared them, and ſworn to them, upon a miſtake, wherein the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were no way excuſable, much leſs juſtifiable, yet God had no where declared his aſſent to, and approbation of this action of the Princes, but had frequently manifeſted his diſlike, and fierce Anger againſt the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for not deſtroying, but making Leagues with others, for which cauſe he reptoved them at <hi>Bochim,</hi> till they wept excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; Threatned them therefore, and as he had denounced, ſo he oft ſold them as Captives, to almoſt all the Nations round about, whom they had ſpared contrary to command, beſides all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168902:10"/>which pretences, by <hi>Saul</hi> no doubt alledged for that ſlaughter committed upon them, the quality of him, and them makes his caſe, and ours of no compariſon together. He a King, and they contemptible drudges, of a curſed Generation. But with us ſworn ſubjects murther'd their Soveraign, the very tongues, mouths, and lips that had vo'wd ſolemn allegiance to him, and to hazard life in his preſervation, and to defend with him his Queen and Progeny, preſume to condemn to death the ſame Royall Perſon, proclaim Traytors his Queen, and Sonnes, yea all that ſhall adhere to them, and aſſert their ſo oft confirmed title, by ſo ſacred and religious oaths. This certainly next to our bleſſed Saviours murther was moſt black and hortible.</p>
            <p n="40">40. Beſides, with Majeſty fell Nobles, and Gentlemen, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and Citizens, of as great repute, as any the Land afforded, who were as undoubtedly Innocent, as cruelly ſlaughtered, yea their crime objected, was honeſty, the pretence of taking them off, was a colourable mock-juſtice, yet in their own conſcience they knew their Courts to be only Snares and Engines, to do ſuch work, which by no known Law of the Land, nor in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular form of proceeding, could be effected. If then <hi>Saul</hi>'s bloudy-fact were revenged, with three yeares famine, and after that with the death of Seven of his Sonnes; I tremble to think, what vengeance the Lord may take of us, for this bloud, unleſs our moſt honourable Lords, and thoſe other worthy Patriots of the Engliſh Nation, the Houſe of Commons, by their pious wiſdom, and juſt ſeverity, againſt unpardonable malefactors, ſcatter that black cloud of Gods judgments, which is already gathering, and who knowes how ſoon it may overſpread the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="41">41. Breaking Parliaments, ſubverting Laws, horrible Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion by Confiscations, Sequeſtrations, decimations, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, frequent ſending out of Town, ſetting up Uſurpers, making the Nobles more contemptible than any generous Spirits could bear, are unparallel'd Treaſons, and being againſt man more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, may be famous objects of Pardon, even to aſtoniſhment, but to indemnifie ſuch horrible guilt of bloud, is to preſume to do that on Earth, which God will never ſet his ſeal to, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168902:10"/>in Heaven: It is for man to exceed his Commiſſion, which preſumption he and his Poſterity may have cauſe to bewail with bitter tears, when it is too late to remedy.</p>
            <p n="42">42. My Lords and Gentlemen, although in a Parliamentary way of Convention, with his Majeſties Royal aſſent concurring, you have great, (I had almoſt ſaid unlimited) power, which is true in a ſenſe, nothing, that is mearly humane, can bound you, yet there are bounds ſet even to you, by the hand of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, no leſs dreadfull than the bounds of <hi>Sinai,</hi> which you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tranſgreſs, but you ſtreight incurre the diſpleaſure of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging Deity, whoſe Angel with his flaming ſword, is forthwith over your head, and ſpeedy Judgement ready to overtake you, and treading upon your heels. Nor will this be your private ſin, but (as perſons in truſt) you contract a fatal ſcore, whereof God alone knows how many thouſands muſt be the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters. One of thoſe immovable bounds is the guilt of bloud, which debt, if you remit, as to the penalty, it were well if you could croſs it out of Gods book, but that's impoſſible, bloud only is to be the payment, though it is in your choyce, whether this ſhall be guilty, or other innocent bloud, which God as a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord, perhaps will take, and place both the former and latter, to their account, at whoſe door neglect lies.</p>
            <p n="43">43. Believe it my Lods and Gentlemen, the perſons concerned in that deteſtable murther of his Majeſty, are not all compriſed in the liſt of thoſe who ſate in the High Court of Mock-juſtice, that day when ſentence was paſt, that whole pretended Court, or rather pack of Bloud-hounds, were but the tool and inſtrument in the hand of ſome deviliſh Workman, Journey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> employed by others who contrived the Plot, and ſet them on work, among whoſe number ſome were more actively daring, and openly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, as well to give countenance to, as incourage the reſt, (who were perſons qualifyed to ſerve their turn, and pickt here and there, as they came to hand) others of the grand contrivers, were more wary, and reſerved, who for fear of after-reckonings ſlipt behind the Curtain, gave aim unto, and directed the Actors, <hi>Haſlerig, Vane, Lenthall,</hi> and others of that gang, had as deep hand in that Crimſon fact, as any who were preſent at ſentence, or confirmed it under hand and Seal,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168902:11"/>
            <p n="44">44. That there is no pleading for murther where all are prin cipalls, the Law of our land makes evident, leſs for Royall mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as is clear by that Scripture-rule, which ſaith. <hi>Who can lift up his hand, againſt the Lords anointed and be guiltleſs;</hi> and moſt plainly confirmed by the pattern of <hi>David,</hi> who commanded that fooliſh <hi>Amalekite</hi> forthwith to be ſlain, who in hope of reward, accuſed himſelf, that he had at the requeſt of <hi>Saul,</hi> diſpatcht his life (when paſt hope of recovery, by reaſon of his mortall wounds) ſending him to his long home with this farewell, <hi>thy bloud be upon thine own head, foraſmuch as thou haſt confeſt the lifting up thine hand againſt the Lords anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="45">45. Yet as the firſt plotter and contriver of a horrid fact, if eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially he ſtand by, and encourage, adviſe, aſſiſt, juſtify, and reward the Actor, is the more unpardonably guilty, ſo thoſe who appointed an high Court of Juſtice, nominated the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, commiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ated, impowered and warranted them, in what they were to act, were indeed the ſuperlatiue Traytors, and moſt guilty of bloud.</p>
            <p n="46">46. And among thoſe there are yet degrees, ſome were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Lawyers, and could not be ignorant of the Law of the Land, their conſcience told them in the very act of endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to try their King for life, in ſuch an unheard of Court, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were above all, moſt tranſcendent Traytors.</p>
            <p n="47">47. In which crew, as all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Subjects, ſo many were his Majeſties actuall ſervants, as <hi>Vane, Mildmay, Danvers, Holland,</hi> and others, whoſe fact ſurpaſſeth ſo far the reſt, as it is more deteſtable for a ſervant, than for a ſtranger to kill his Maſter, by our Law made petty Treaſon, and more ſeverely puniſhed. Some were ſervants in favour, and places of more than ordinary truſt, and were rewarded ſo largely, as argued a bountifull Prince, and them on that account, Monſters in nature, who durſt abet; much more actually commit ſuch a villany upon ſo gracious a Lord, ſo loving and bountifull a Maſter.</p>
            <p n="48">48. Their declarations after the fact challenged the imagined repute thereof to themſelves, for as they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e no ſcruple to call themſelves the Parliament and ſupream power of <hi>England,</hi> ſo they aſcribed to themſelves the aboliſhing Kingſhip; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168902:11"/>rejected the whole line of the murther'd King, declar'd for a Common-wealth whithout King or Houſe of Lords, fram'd and impoſed upon all an engagement to that purpoſe, which argues plainly, that thoſe who were the Major part of that <hi>Junto,</hi> who voted an high Court of Juſtice, and who confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon them ſuch power, were the plotters and Authors of what was by the others acted, the firſt of the two moſt inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though all unpardonable.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Beſides theſe, there were contrivers of Petitions, that all great offendors might be brought to juſtice, which were accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly framed, and preſented both from the City and mutinous Army, by which his ſacred Majeſty was at firſt deſigned to be made a bloudy ſacrifice, under the notion of the greateſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, being brought to juſtice, Adjutant Generall <hi>Allen</hi> at the diſpoſition of Uſurping <hi>Richard,</hi> wrote a Pamphet, to remind the grand Officers how the Army were in a wilderneſs of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in the year 1647. and how they at <hi>Windſor</hi> ſeverall dayes together, had ſought God by faſting and prayer, and how he at laſt brought them to an unanimous reſolve, that they would fight the <hi>Scots,</hi> and labour to quell the threatning inſurrections in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts, and in caſe God anſwered their prayers, they would, as a religious return of thankfulneſs, revenge the bloudſhed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in theſe Warres, upon that bloudy man, as he was pleaſed to ſtile his Sacred Majeſty of bleſſed memory. So that there was a conſpiracy in the Army, with a part of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to murther the King long before; who therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending fear, with their Speaker fled to the Head-quarters, were brought back by the Armies force, the Commons Houſe purged, the Lords Houſe turn'd out of doors. Here my Lords and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen was the plot, after which an high Court of Juſtice was called, and impowered to put what before was contrived, in execution.</p>
            <p n="50">50. Nor were they ignorant of what villany they went about, or the way muſt be made, by breaking the Seal Royall, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a new one, becauſe the King could not be judicially procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed againſt without commiſſion, nor any commiſſion in force againſt him, ſigned with his own Seal, which argued as premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168902:12"/>ſo deſperate malice, joyned with knowledg ſufficient; they underſtood the fact, &amp; its difficulty, as well as its danger, yet reſolved to leap over mountaines themſelves, rather than not perform this butchery.</p>
            <p n="51">51. Mr. <hi>Milton</hi> in anſwer to <hi>Salmaſius</hi> gives the whole glory of this Heroick action (as he call'd it) to the Engliſh Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And indeed it was properly their act originally, the Judges did but only repreſent them; acted by their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who in this are inexcuſable alſo, that they took a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and put it in execution againſt their undoubted King, which involved them alike in the guilt of perjury and Treaſon, being equally ſworn to his Allegiance, and by this act (however Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated) they were queſtionleſs murtherers.</p>
            <p n="52">52. This Honourable houſe of Commons in their late anſwer to his Majeſties moſt gracious Letter, have this like expreſſion, that the abhorred villanies, perpetrated upon his Majeſties Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Father (of bleſſed memory) could never poſſibly have been brought to that paſs, had not their priviledges been ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully violated; firſt, that of Englands Parliament nothing was left remaining but a <hi>Mock-Junto.</hi> By that diſcovering their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be, that they who in order to that butchery, committed ſuch unheard of Rapes upon the Parliament, were of all others far the moſt guilty, And therefore deſerving moſt ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p n="53">53. To come now to the high Court of juſtice, and take a view of their proceedings, ſome ſate to the laſt, and paſſed the ſentence actually under their hands and Seales, others ſate at firſt only, ſome ſate till the laſt, and then diſappeared.</p>
            <p>All are alike guilty, for his Sacred Majeſty demurr'd at firſt to the Juriſdiction of the Court, they who then ſate, aſſerted their own juriſdiction, declaring that they were ſatiſfied in it; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to plead poſitively, and to own the Court, or elſe the default ſhould be marked for a contempt; this was in effect his Majeſties doom; he as a conſtant aſſertor of the Lawes, and Liberties of the Nation, was unſatiſfied with their Autority; and reſolved rather to dy, than by a Plea to own them a juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction at all; (much leſs over him, their King) theſe peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168902:12"/>villanies aſſert their own Jurisdiction, tye him up to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, or to be recorded for his Contempt, upon which account, the third default was to be accounted final, then ſome with-drew, and account themſelves thus excuſed from his bloud, by not ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at laſt, when ſentence was given; yet proteſt not againſt the proceedings of the reſt; when as in truth they impounded, as I may ſay, ſhackled his Majeſty, and fitted him for the block, with-drawing out of a guilty fear, when the blow was to be given, being aſſured, that there were Bloud-hounds enough left ſitting to worrey him: not a man more than other can be excuſed of the murther, unleſs it appear, that they ſhewed their diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and diſlike of proceedings, to be the cauſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing afterward to ſit.</p>
            <p n="54">54. Laſtly, no doubt but many pretended divine Oracles are equally guilty, with the reſt, who counſelled, contrived, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged theſe villanies, which ended in murther, and vouched the holy Writ for their warrant, to provoke to the attempt, and defended the fact afterward, both by preaching and writing; the Prieſt who confeſſed, and abſolved the Powder-traytors was found as guilty, and ſuffered as deeply, as any among them; <hi>Peeters</hi> and <hi>Goodwyn</hi> may be named, and many more pointed at; but theſe two, were as <hi>Joab</hi> to the vvoman of <hi>Tekoah</hi> they had a hand in the whole, from beginning to end, yea, ſo far are they more puniſhable, but how much they abuſed Scripture to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and as it were entitle God himſelf to the murther.</p>
            <p n="55">55. To deſcend from this black ſubject, and bloudy diſcourſe, to take a view of more private murthers, tragical enough, yet for which ſomething may be ſaid in behalf of many concerned therein.</p>
            <p n="56">56. When grave, learned, and able Lawyers, ſhall declare the Authority of a pretended High Court of Juſtice to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and perſonally act therein, either as Preſident, as <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſle,</hi> or by drawing up charges againſt Priſoners, and calling them before ſuch to the Barre, aggravating crimes againſt them, ſolliciting for Juſtice to be done on them in the name of the Common-Wealth, and in all things, avowing them a Court of Judicature; I marvel not, if many men unskil'd in the Law, ſit among the reſt, and act confidently.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168902:13"/>
            <p n="57">57. If the Facts for which they are tryed, be by Lawyer declared high Treaſon, and Capital, and Witneſſes procured to teſtifie the ſame, (how ſuborned is not now the ſubject of our Enquiry nor how prompted in their Evidence, by the Attorney General) if Lawyers affirm the tryal to be carryed on according to Law, and ſome reputed godly Divines aſſure them the way is of God; no wonder if the Priſoner be convicted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and yet God forbid, half the Judges guilty of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or bloud, though concurring in ſentence.</p>
            <p n="58">58. However, thoſe who adviſe the erecting ſuch a Court, out of deſign to butcher the Parties intended for tryal, becauſe they know that the crime objected, is indeed no crime by the Law of the Land: They who give commiſſion under the pretended Seal of <hi>England,</hi> for trying ſuch offenders by nominated Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ers, yet know that very Commiſſion to be illegal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, and yet intended as an Engine to remove ſome out of the way that are before marked for deſtruction; they (laſtly) who proſecute the Priſoners at the Barre of ſuch a Court, The Judge alſo, who ſits in Judgement upon, and pronounceth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt them; though both Judge, Attorney and Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor know the Priſoners not to deſerve ſo much as bonds by the known fundamental Laws of the Land, and the Power by which they pretend to Act, to be uſurped and illegal, nay, contrary to Law, which they (in formality) are ſworn to maintain, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Juſtice accordingly, all theſe (doubtleſly) are a pack of Conſpirators againſt the Innocent bloud, which is thus ſhed by them, and moſt cruel, unpardonable murtherers; this for leſs publick butcheries committed upon the ſcore of pretended High Courts of Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="59">59. Two private caſes remains yet, as namely that of <hi>Lucas,</hi> and <hi>Liſle,</hi> and the other of <hi>Penruddok</hi> and <hi>Grove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former were ſhot to death in cool bloud, by ſentence of a Court Mattial; the latter condemned by (that great Prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator) <hi>Glyn,</hi> who cauſed them to be indicted for taking up Arms againſt <hi>Cromwell,</hi> upon that Law, which makes it Treaſon to levy War againſt the King, no Law being then hatched to ſecure that Uſurper, and although the Priſoners pleading to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168902:13"/>defended themſelves unanſwerably, and made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear (by that very Law,) that <hi>Oliver</hi> was the Traytor in making War upon them, who proclaimed, and fought for that King whom he oppoſed, yet this moſt unrighteous Judge made the Law (violently) to ſpeak againſt it ſelf, by his interpretation, and ſo condemned the moſt innocent Priſoners, whom after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, with others, (upon the ſame ſcore,) he cauſed to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, for which, if ever Judge in <hi>England</hi> deſerved exemplary death, certainly he fell as much, if not more.</p>
            <p n="60">60. Thus, moſt honourable Lords and Gentlemen, having ſpoken concerning the perſons who they are; give me leave to adde ſome conſiderations, which ſpeak them uncapable of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, unleſs we intend ſuch vengeance to follow their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which God (if it be his will) prevent, and by the way, I ſhall obviate what objections may be brought againſt this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Juſtice, or arguments to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="61">61. Conſider, I beſeech you; Firſt, the crimes and the men, whether or no, they be fit objects of Mercy, Pardon and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity. Secondly, if they be, whether it is convenient and expedient to let them find ſo great a meaſure of it, and taſte it ſo largely, and I doubt not but upon enquiry, your wiſdoms will with me conclude in the negative, notwithſtanding what ever may be indiſcreetly argued in favour of them.</p>
            <p n="62">62. In order then to proceed; Firſt preſents it ſelf their Fact, and next their manner of acting; Laſtly, their behaviour after it, in all which it is too manifeſt, that as they are beyond, and above Pardon, ſo they are below pity.</p>
            <p n="63">63. Their crime, my Lords and Gentlemen, is Murther, of it ſelf unpardonable, but in them aggravated by Perjury, Malice, inhumane Cruelty, juſtifying thereof under pretence of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the better to ſecure themſelves from Juſtice, they ſpared no manner of Villany; which a dextrous pernicious wit could prompt, or a ſeared conſcience commit. Their murther hath this aſtoniſhing addition, or rather Complement of guilt, in that its object was their King, to whom they were moſt ſacredly and religiouſly obliged, by reiterated Oaths, not only impoled, but by themſelves voluntarily made, and ſolemnly entred into,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168902:14"/>this is the crime of many, nay, moſt of them, beſides other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate murthers, which on their part have the aggravations of malice, and inhumane cruelty on the ſufferers, that they were perſons of Piety, Eſteem, Honour and Faithfulneſs to their King and Countrey, of whom ſeveral excelled (in true worth) all their Martherers together.</p>
            <p n="64">64. My Lords and Gentlemen, if to murther a private man, of no eſteem, little worth, perhaps vicious, debauched, and a burthen to thoſe with whom he lives, deſerve death unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, and our Law juſtly condemns, and executes (in ſuch a caſe) the murtherers, though perhaps many, and otherwiſe, each far ſurpaſſing the party ſlain; ſhall our King (worth ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Subjects,) our eminent Lords &amp; Gentry, our godly Divines and Citizens, be murthered, by the worſt of the Nation (for real worth,) and among ſo many murtherers, ſo few be pick'd out, (of whom many fled) to be made examples, when they can be catcht? when the whole number (if taken) amounts not to the fourth part of thoſe who by them have been formally butchered, beſides the numberleſs multitude of thoſe who have been otherwiſe ſlain, ſtarved, ruined and deſtroyed by means of that firſt Heaven-daring butchery. Shall <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> that infamous Lecher, who having among Strumpets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed his Patrimony, hath long lain in Gaole, to the defrauding his Creditors, be accounted (when he is taken,) a competent Sacrifice in lieu of his Sacred Majeſty, Lord <hi>Capel, Hamilton,</hi> and <hi>Holland?</hi> ſo <hi>Cornelius Holland,</hi> the <hi>Linke-boy,</hi> who hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Eſtate, but what is the price of bloud, and reward of his villanies, be given up to Juſtice (when he is catcht alſo) in revenge of <hi>Hewits, Slingsby's Yeomans,</hi> and <hi>Butchers</hi> bloud? <hi>Thomas Scot,</hi> that Saint, (who beſides his other villanies, moſt ungraciouſly, paid his wife <hi>Grace</hi> in the ſame coin, which he in exchange of greater pieces, received from his girls at a vaulting School, but peppered her ſo the wrong way, that ſhe ſtank the ſooner, and lies buried in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) be made exemplary, (when he likewiſe comes to hand) in lieu of Mr. <hi>Love, Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons, Buſhel,</hi> Col. <hi>Gerard,</hi> and <hi>Vowel,</hi> and ſo the reſt? Or muſt all theſe be made the price of Royal bloud only? Certainly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168902:14"/>Gentlemen, this will be to value his ſacred Perſon, leſs than the <hi>Scots</hi> did, who ſold him (in life) for two hundred thouſand pounds, not becauſe they eſteem'd him worth no more, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was all they could get for him; Had his murtherers been twiſe as many, his worth and value was ſo ineſtimable, that all had made too mean a ſacrifice for his bloud.</p>
            <p n="65">65. That murther of his Sacred Majeſty, brought upon them all the bloud which had been ſhed in <hi>England,</hi> and was the cauſe of all the reſt which was ſhed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> The King in wiſdom, foreſaw the end of the War, levied againſt him, and therefore defended himſelf. So many of the Parliament as were ſincere, abhorred (as by their declarations appeared) thoſe very thoughts, for which end they framed a vow, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, and after joyned with the <hi>Scots</hi> in their League and Covenant, (not ſuſpecting this <hi>Viper</hi> hidden under the green hearbs,) raiſed therefore, as Commiſſionated all their forces for the Kings defence, whereas his murther at laſt, verified the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of his Majeſty, gave the lye to all the Parliaments pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and made it appear, that this Tragedy was the end of all thoſe ſeveral years wars, and incredible civil blond ſhed; Good God! Should theſe men now be pardoned, what can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined? but that the Parliament in their Vowes and Covenant, did all, (both Lords and Commons,) prevaricate and juggle; The deteſtation of a fact, is ever judged by the animadverſion made upon it. Talk till Doomes-day, yet none will believe that the Lords and Commons abhorre that murther, and repute it the Nations infamy reſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Vows, Oaths and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants broken therein, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontrivers, Plotters, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Actors, are almoſt all pardoned by whole ſale, except a few, who in effect have pardoned themſelves by flight.</p>
            <p n="66">66. My Lords and Gentlemen, becauſe of Oaths, and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Land hath a long time mourned, not ſo much for that Oaths were made, but becauſe no better kept: If you were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in what you ſwore, you cannot but revenge the ſhamefull breach thereof, with all imaginable ſeverity; (truſt me) lenity herein will ſpeak aloud to your reproach, both while you live, and while your memory laſteth, that you are pretty well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168902:15"/>as to the fact, when you diſmiſs with free pardon, ſuch a gang of Malefactors, Religion hath been ſcandalized ſo fowly by this means, (the Proteſtant eſpecially) that were it only to ſhew your deteſtation thereof, ſuch counſels would take no place in your honourable breaſts. It is the only convincing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that you were immovably firm to your Oaths and Vowes, when you are irreconcilable to thoſe, who with ſuch abominable aggravations broke them.</p>
            <p n="67">67. Thoſe who at preſent are remote from you, and for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſhall be long after you, can take notice of no ground of ſo large an extent of Pardon, but that you either judge the fact not deſerving greater puniſhment, or that you are afraid to do Juſtice upon them; and to ſpeak plainly, ſuch lenity as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended (I hope not intended in this Caſe,) will leave ſuch a blot upon your Honours and Wiſdoms, as cannot be born with credit, nor wiped off by any poſſible future zeal or induſtry. He who is eaſily perſwaded to re nit ſo groſſe villanies, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies leave a ſuſpicion, that he would not hardly have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to be concerned therein, had not politick conſiderations (more than conſcience) deterred him. It is the glory of a man to paſs by the greateſt injury done to himſelf, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, but to forgive what is done againſt Gods Majeſty, with the like readineſs and facility, argues that ſuch a man hath but little honour for God.</p>
            <p n="68">68. My Lords and Gentlemen, its poſſible for any man to be ſo out of reach of othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not to be expoſed to their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, cenſures and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>erſions, nor is it in your power to regulate them, but every man will follow the dictates of his own reaſon, and what appears thereto.</p>
            <p n="69">69. The grounds of this over-flowing mercy, and inlarged bowels of compaſſion, (believe it) will be judged one or all of theſe: Either a low eſteem you had of his Sacred Majeſty; or a private diſlike of him, which makes you account his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val out of the way, ſome conſiderable balance, to counterpoiſe the execrable, horrible Treachery, and perjurious cruelty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in his death or that you give ſome credit to the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions laid againſt him, and ſo reckon him as deſerving the thing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168902:15"/>he ſuffered, though perhaps you diſliked the manner. Or that you were your ſelves guilty herein more than you would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have known; and therefore pardon ſo many, leaſt they ſhould ſpeak plainer of your ſelves, than you would be willing to have heard. Or that, notwithſtanding your Oaths and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, you intended the ſame thing in your own way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and ſo were only prevented. Or that you under-hand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to what was acted, and moſt of you by a patient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, upon ſecluſion of the forty Commoners, gave oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to what was afterward perpetrated.</p>
            <p n="70">70. Theſe ſuſpicions, my Lords and Gentlemen, though, I hope, ye believe them falſe and groundleſs, yet on my credit are more than whiſper'd (among very ſober men,) upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this too comprehenſive act of grace, which is expected, and would make viler than dirt the bloud, not only of many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtate-Martyrs, and his ſacred Majeſty himſelf, but alſo of all thoſe whoſe lives have been prodigally ſpent, to ſubdue the King, and his friends, and bring him into a capacity of becoming the ſubject of ſo abominable a Tragedy, as alſo of rejecting and keeping in exile his matchleſs (for reall worth) and yet by unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell'd villany, proſcribed heir, with two Incomparable pieces of true Princely gallantry, the Royall Dukes, of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi> The grinding oppreſſors alſo of theſe three Nations, wherein all the Kings put together ſince the Conqueſt have been exceeded, will be notably rewarded, when out of more than an hundred unpardonable Murtherers, beſides incomputable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of high traytors, perhaps five ſhall dye, and thirty or forty of thoſe be ſqueezed a little in their Eſtates, who have cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly ruined many hundreds, ſequeſtred, and forced to mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous unreaſonable compoſitions, many thouſands; totally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated the Eſtates of ſix times their number, and by taxes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, impoſitions, decimations, frequent impriſonments, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged plots and fines thereupon, have beggar'd a thouſand at leaſt, for every man deſigned for nominall confiſcation of Eſtate, which indeed will prove ſcarce the plucking away by law one third part of what they before violently and cruelly raviſht from the true owners without all colour of Law, rather againſt it.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:168902:16"/>
            <p n="71">71. My Lords and Gentlemen, can it be imagined, that <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Lenthall,</hi> who had for a fee five pounds for every compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe number was reckoned by one to be fourſcore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand (ſuppoſe really half the number which was the leaſt) beſides other places of vaſt prodigious gain, enjoyed by him above board, nor will any rationall man queſtion, but he had private wayes of indirect gain, beyond what can be made now appear upon confiſcation will be found the Maſter of one tith of what he is (beyond contradiction) owner, queſtionleſs no, ſuch villaines as he, alwayes had that of reaſon, to fear what we ſe hapned, nay, they had no rationall ground to hope for ſo long proſperity in villany; upon which jealouſy he, and many of his ſtamp, no doubt, made ſuch ſecret proviſion, that ſpating their life (on ſuch termes) is like a School-boyes whipping, (when over) the fear proving more than the ſmart, they have time and occaſion given, to laugh at the ſupineſs of their Judges, and to pleaſe themſelves, how they give the firſt, the ſoundeſt, and moſt ſmarting blow.</p>
            <p n="72">72. Who would not, if they had opportunity again, be ſuch Rogues upon the like termes, be as cruell as poſſible, as guilty, as wit can invent, the Devill ſuggeſt, or a curſed diſpoſition make, commit villanies to the utmoſt extent of power, ſtop only, where it is not poſſible to go further, continue as long, as by Helliſh policy is deviſable, oppreſs the Nation, till nothing be left further to ſqueeze; yet at laſt, when our own ungodlineſs hath enſnared us, and a reſtoration made, becauſe we can no longer hinder it, nineteen of twenty ſhall have peremptory pardon, the reſt law, fly, if they can, but if unavoidable they be catcht, they ſhall have fair tryall themſelves, who never allowed others any, come my Maſters, find but you conſciences, and here are all the incouragements to monſtrous villany, that are poſſible.</p>
            <p n="73">73. My Lords and Gentlemen, as to the heynouſneſs of this fact, I humbly intreat you to conſider, it is that, which you would have your Kings by agreement diſabled to pardon, and juſtly, becauſe God is poſitive therein, whoever ſhedds mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed. Will you reſtrain your King, yet your ſelves do it; ſhall not a private man be murther'd,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168902:16"/>but his bloud requir'd, and ſhall your King? If ſo, woe to thee <hi>England!</hi> What will be thy doom <hi>London!</hi> Would God you had the Art to confine divine Judgments within your own walls, if needs you will pluck them down with ſuch Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ropes.</p>
            <p n="74">74. You are my Lords and Gentlemen, every one of you put in a publick capacity, do not (I humbly entreat you) offer your ſelves (now) as bayle to Gods Juſtice, for ſuch impardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble offenders. The doom of <hi>Ahab</hi> is not to be neglected. Becauſe thou haſt let go a man, whom I appointed to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy life ſhall go for his. A diſcreet man would hardly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage life for life, for an infamous thief or high-way man. Better be bayle for ten ſuch, than for one of theſe high Court of Juſtice men, thoſe eſpecially, who are guilty of Royall bloud, where God himſelf keeps the recogniſance ſtrickly, and will not fail to require it ſeverely.</p>
            <p n="75">75. Your wiſdoms are I doubt not adviſed that forfeiture of eſtate, (if it could be totall) is no adequate ſatiſfaction, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent recompenſe either to the Law, or Gods Juſtice, where both life and ſtate are due, and confiſcate; the one legally given to the King, for his loſs of a Subject, the other indiſpenſably due to that vengeance, which will take no triffe in recompence, but only life for life, and bloud for bloud.</p>
            <p n="76">76. To conclude this head, concerning the nature of their offence, it is to be minded univerſally, that puniſhment is a glaſs, in which we contemplate, and diſcover either the true nature of the crime, or the unanſwerable ſenſe of the judg, perhaps the joy of reſtoration hath obliterated the remembrance of our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance nor will ſuffer us to reflect upon our former ſlavery, and miſery, (with their cauſes) if ſo, God who when he was lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his people unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> reminded them of the houſe of Bondage, with thunder, lightning, and Earthquakes, may alſo rub up our memories, both with a witneſs and vengeance.</p>
            <p n="77">77. From the crime I beſeech your wiſdomes to caſt your eye upon the perſons, and ſee how well they appear deſerving mercy.</p>
            <p>How have they heapt villanies one upon another, as the Giants
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168902:17"/>in their Warre againſt Heaven heapt <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> or as waves in a ſtorm follow one upon the neck of another. Believe it Gentlemen; they are not men of <hi>David</hi>'s ſpirit, whoſe heart ſmote him, for cutting off <hi>Sauls</hi> skirt, but when it was motioned, to go over to him and ſlay him ſleeping, he rejected the offer with deteſtation: from Monſtrous impieties, they came to that amazing Butchery committed on the King, not after found they any ſtroke at heart, but only of grief, that they had not all the Royall branches in their power to chop down in one day.</p>
            <p n="78">78. Prodigious Malefactors they are, who took their firſt riſe of Monſtrous villany at the rending up the two howſes of Parliament by the Root, (not conſidering the firſt pretended ground of the Warre, was becauſe the King demanded to tryall, (ſecured not, nor ſecluded) five Commoners, and one Peer, no bones at laſt were made of either proteſtations or pretences, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing accounted by them ſordid; they pretended a fear, and fled to the Army from petitioning unarmed apprentiſes, (ſpirits oft before by themſelves conjured up, and laid again, without dread, while they came and requeſted bloud, warre, and confuſion, but now they are dreadfull when they petition for ſettlement, a thing hatefull to thoſe who had been, and expected to be ſuch gainers by trouble and diſtraction.) 'Twas that in Church and ſtate they aimed at, in ſuch waters they longed to fiſh, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Cromwell, Heſlerigge, Vane, Lenthall, Scot,</hi> &amp;c. would loſe their longing, they reſolved with their father <hi>Pluto,</hi> as he is brought in thus ſpeaking by <hi>Claudian,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>— Patefacta ciebo</l>
                  <l>Tartara, Saturni veteres laxabo catenas,</l>
                  <l>Obducam tenebris lucem, compage ſolutâ</l>
                  <l>Fulgidus umbroſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcebitur axis averno.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="79">79. My Lords and Gentlemen, conſider what a coal you are ſcraping, to give your names to poſterity an indelible ſmut, or mark, and what unfeigned repentance is requiſite from you, as ſoon as this act is concluded, in reference to the warres paſt. If it be moſt certain, <hi>Bonus Civis initia belli Civilis invitus ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipit,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168902:17"/>extrema non libentèr perſequitur,</hi> there is need of all the heart-breaking poſſible on their ſide, who roſe in Arms, hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo many lives, ſpent ſo much treaſure and blood to reſtrain his Majeſty (of Sacred Memory) from vexing the people, with thoſe Flea bites, in compariſon of the devouring extortions which theſe villains afterwards oppreſſed, yea almoſt deſtroyed them with; To prohibit his infringing the Parliamentary pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, impeaching five Members, while theſe impeach ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at once, and compell them beyond Sea, without proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Tryall: &amp; after ſecure above forty; force away two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, diſcard the Houſe of Peers, caſhiere their priviledges, murther the King, root up the Law, ſet up Arbitrary Taxes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, Exciſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Commiſſion monſtrous unheard of Courts, and in them hunt to death as many, and for what they pleaſe, where no Law of the Land ſpeakes them ſo much as Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall; yet for all theſe Treaſons, and murthers, ſcarce ten of the moſt infamous Commoners in <hi>England,</hi> are thought fit to die; when for the life of one man (<hi>Parſons</hi> by Name, Lieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel to the Drayman, <hi>Pride,</hi> and of as obſcure origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall as his Collonel) ſlain by accident on the High way, not a man concerned in that Robbery, eſcaped the Gallows; and when for one Houſe-Robbery, it is frequent to hang nine or ten, ſometimes ſixteen, or twenty, yet all of them infinitely ſhort of theſe Villains in crimes.</p>
            <p n="80">80. How for future dare a Judge ſit on the Benth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn a poor petty Thief, a Coyner of money; one in a paſſion guilty of ſtabbing; or a poor Wenth for a Child thrown into a Jakes, which none knows, if or no it were born alive; nay any murther, when ſuch unparallel'd Theeves; Traytors beyond preſident, Murtherers to amazement, and aſhoniſhment, are either judged not fit to die, or at leaſt not convenient, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſhould looſe ſo many Subjects.</p>
            <p n="81">81. Bleſſe us good God! Subjects of which no King need be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proud, or deſirous; A way to make a happy Prince, when he ſhall ſcarce go any where, but (conſidering their number) he may meet with one or other of them, and point at them, There goes one who murther'd my Royall Father; baniſhed me, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated my revenues, reduced to extream ſtraits my Mother and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168902:18"/>Brothers, with all my true friends and Relations, butchered my Subjects, and illegally extorted from them a thouſand times mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n they would ſuffer their Leige and King to levy though with advice of his Judges, but made warre upon him, and took his life upon this pretence: Theſe good Subjects are left me, through the piety and wiſdome of my two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſutable objects of my Royall Mercy and Pardon.</p>
            <p n="82">82. Divinely Gracious Prince, theſe are not objects of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, God will not have it ſo, having expreſſed his will, in hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their hearts to the laſt; When God hardned the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſo as to follow the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the very bowels of the deep Sea, his providence ſpake plainly that his intention was to drown them. Prudent Generalls uſe to give no quarter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Gatriſons, which refuſing all offers of mercy, ſtand out to the laſt; againſt whom nevertheleſſe, they have no quarrel but open Hoſtility, and plain intereſt of warr: How much leſs are theſe Villaines, who had forfeited their lives unpardonably for any one of their inferiour murthers, to expect pardon after ſo great guilt, ſo long continued in impenitently, and perſervered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very laſt.</p>
            <p n="83">83. Who can imagine that they repent any thing but the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a period thus to their Uſurpation and Tyranny? who had heard <hi>Haſterigge</hi> threatning to fight all over again; proteſting he had rather been buryed in his grave, than ſeen the ſecluded Members reſtored, that had obſerved the Rumpers abjuring his Sacred Majeſty, and whole Royall ſtock, with all Kingly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſending the Generall into the City, to pluck up their Poſts, take away their Chains, Demoliſh their Gates, impriſon their Members, with a further charge (as is reported) to break down their Wall; Hang up their Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That had ſeen <hi>Hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> a little before, marching into the City, and with armed men, killing poore unarmed Apprentices, barely for aſſaying to deliver a Petition to their Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their diſtreſſes, and indeavour a remedy: That had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the ſtickling Rulers of the Roſt, upon the laſt ſitting of the <hi>Mock Iunto,</hi> to frame a Petition, and labour others coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to deliver it to their pious conſideration, to have the Oath of Abjuration impoſed upon all Miniſters, Schoolmaſters, and thoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168902:18"/>in places of truſt, upon penalty of being ejected, in caſe of refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall: That had obſerved <hi>John Lenthal</hi> buſie in <hi>London,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade from the thoughts of receiving his Sacred Majeſty; reviling him, calling him Baſtard, Sonn of a Tyrant, Jeſuited Papiſt; with other horrble amazing reproaches. If theſe be the ſignes of peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent traitors, &amp; murderers, in Gods name let them be pardoned; &amp; at once let all villains paſt and to come, be with one Act of Grace forgiven in <hi>England</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="84">84. What hopes of their amendment, who have outvyed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Gunpowder-Traitors; and Jeſuites moſt dangerous tenents, they have out-acted and defended? who can expect any good nature yet to lodge in thoſe breaſts, who have proved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Monſters in Nature? deſperately ſeared Conſciences, to whom Rebellion and treaſon is become habituall; Hypocrites in grain, who crave a Bleſſing, commonly before their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Faſt and pray, to ſeek Gods aſſiſtance on them, and give ſolemn thanks after them. No expectation of good from ſuch who have turn'd the moſt abhominable impieties into a ſet Form of Religion; and have uſ'd of late years, no other ſervice of God than this.</p>
            <p n="85">85. It's ſome good ſign when men are aſham'd of a bad acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtudy to conceal it, and excuſe it, but to declare wickedneſs openly, argues one paſt all grace, A whore that ownes her ſelf one, and is proud to be accounted ſo, gives ſmall hopes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment; but ſhe who pleads for it as a lawfull trade, may be given over as deſperate.</p>
            <p n="86">86. Beſides the guilt of not only blood, but frequent, horrible, amazing Murtherers, compleated with King-killing and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, hath an irreſiſtable power of hardning their hearts, who are guilty; and if theſe be ſpared, God may in Judgement ſuffer their principles to be penally inſnaring; it is a fatall courteſie, which brings a certain curſe on a mans ſelf, and intailes it to his poſterity.</p>
            <p n="87">87. Conſider Gentlemen, how they dealt with others, as Souldiers, with all the <hi>Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh</hi> in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Warrs, who were conſtantly excluded the benefit of eitſter quarter, or Articles of ſurrender, in deteſtation of the bloody tradegy acted by them on the Proteſtants, in <hi>Tredigh, Wexford</hi> and other places in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168902:19"/>Kallendar-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> can witneſſe for them, that having to do with Chriſtians, they made no ſcruple of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thouſands to the Sword, who would not ſurrender up Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftles and Garriſons to their imperious demand: And as Judges, it is well known that none of the Iriſh were ſuffered to ſcape with life, who could be convicted of the Murther of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant; Can any Law be more juſt than their own? Our King, Nobles, Knights, Gentry, Divines, and Citizens, were of no leſſe eſteem than thoſe murdered Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the firſt valuable with ten thouſand; Nor were the Murtherers leſs barbarous then the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebells.</p>
            <p n="88">88. But above all conſider their imperious pride, peremtory ſaucinefs, and monſtrous cruelty in the tryall, ſentencing and condemning the King, breaking his Seal Royall, and making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to render the murder feſible, under a colour of <hi>Mock Juſtice,</hi> refuſing his demurrs, not admitting him to ſpeak for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felf, unleſſe he would own them a Court of Judicature, having power over him, and take a Tryall from them, ſo to betray <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> liberties at once, their appointing the place at his own Gate, to go out of the Window of his former Princely pleaſure, and Royal Magnificence, unto the Stage of his finall bloody Tradgedy; where pullies were prepared with Ropes, perforce to compell him to bow his Royall Head, and lay his neck on the block, had he refuſed to ſubmit willingly, the ghaſtly Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners with ugly Viſors, repreſenting truly what they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed within, who durſt act ſuch a deed; The flouriſhing of Weapons in triumph, upon giving that Execrable blow, cutting and wounding any whoſe eyes betrayd a relenting heart, at ſo damnable a ſight, yea, decapitating his harmleſſe Statue upon the Royall Exchange, with an <hi>(Exit Tyrannus)</hi> writ over his place of ſtanding, in deſign to murther his Name and Memory as well as his Body. What ſtony heart can think of this and not melt: &amp; yet ſhall <hi>Waller</hi> (not only one of his fatal Judges, but the deteſtable contriver of that place, and time of his death, which added cruelty to the height of his other Villany) only be plundred of that part of his eſtate which he hath not already made away, or cannot conceal? <hi>Okey</hi> another of that curſed Committee, ſhall he find the like favour? I hope not.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:168902:19"/>
            <p n="89">89. Had any pity or piety been in the breaſts of any of the Junto, their diſowning, proteſting againſt, and diſclaiming the horribleneſs of that fact, had given a preſent check to it, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps daſht it for ever.</p>
            <p n="90">90. Obſerve I beſeech you the uſuall dealing of theſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors againſt others, yea all whom they could inſnare, either as to life or eſtate, or both, what art to intrap? Packing of Judges? Suborning witneſſes, violence in proſecution? And like arts, to make as many, as they deſigned for tuine, to appear guilty, and what mercy at laſt, but cruell extremity? Tis Gods rule and will, that Judgement without mercy ſhould be to him, or them, who ſhewed no mercy.</p>
            <p n="91">91. Thus my Lords and Gentlemen it is evident that neither the fact, nor the perſons deſerve mercy, I ſhall adde a few con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations more to evince the inexpediency of it.</p>
            <p n="92">92. By doing this you will either contradict your own vote, which concluded the fact horrible murther, or give the World to underſtand, that you judge them not all guilty who were act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors; and then what need of pardon? Or you will let the Nation know, that for once you will change Seats with God himſelf, he only can pardon murther, who ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> thou ſhalt not die, but hath forbidden man to do it. If you who cannot pardon the bloud of a Porter, or Waterbearer; will preſume to preferre Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicides, (beſides other murthers they are guilty of) to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty for pardon; It is to be feared you will thus intaile the ſword upon theſe Kingdomes God knowes how long, he that ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> thou ſhalt not die, added, Howbeit the ſword ſhall never depart from thy houſe, in revenge of one <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah:</hi> But here our <hi>David</hi> himſelf was ſlaine, by worſe than <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and beſides him ſeverall ſcores of other perſons of worth, Gallant Commanders, Godly Preachers, eminent Gentlemen, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Citizens, all honeſt, faithfull ſubjects cut off by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, and prodigious Traytors.</p>
            <p n="93">93. What will poſterity judge when they read the hiſtory of theſe times (which he that will be a faithfull hiſtorian muſt pen candidly,) when he ſhall find ſuch a vaſt catalogue of ſtupendious crimes puniſhed (in compariſon) only with a flap of the Fox taile, they muſt needs either diſtruſt the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168902:20"/>of the ſtory, or cenſure the innocency of the Judges; It is an old ſaying, When theeves ſit in judgement one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the triall may be ſerious, but the execution will be but in jeſt. <hi>Facinus quos inquinat, aequat.</hi> Should I read ſuch a ſtory paſt; I ſhould my ſelfe have ſuch thoughts; though I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confidence of your Honors, and that the weekly Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, give not your cordially true ſence and intentions.</p>
            <p n="94">94. Where pardon is ſo large, it is eſteemed an Act not of mercy, ſo much as of politick juſtice, and had the murthers been ſpared on the offenders part, the indemnity could not be too comprehenſive, though if it be ſo large notwithſtanding, the ſame Juſtice will be apprehended therein of which apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſuch like will be the conſtructions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That theſe few who are made exemplary, ſuffer on the ſcore of ſome private grudge and barely in ſtate policy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That what was done by them was honeſt enough, if it could have been as confidently maintained, and defended, as valiantly atchieved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That you are convinced of the rationality of Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall principles, and that if a King upon any ſcore head a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a Civill warre, and be vanquiſhed he is at the victors diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that then oaths ceaſe, when he is unable to protect them, and out of capacity of redeeming himſelf from them, that the fountaine of power is in the people, with which they betruſt their Kings, and may recall it upon his miſgovernment, reaſſume it into their own hands, and try, convict, and puniſh him, even capitally, if they in conſcience judge him guilty, and they will uſe this lenity of yours in pardoning almoſt all who did ſo, as an unanſwerable argument, of theſe forementioned apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That if ever they can get the like opportunity, they may do the ſame againe and hold out finally, if they can; however, if they fail, this will be a preſident, what iſſue they are to expect. My Lords and Gentlemen, it will be the moſt lethall leſſon, that can be taught Subjects, to let them know, that King-kiling is pardonable (as to life) to twenty for one, if they can have but wit to ſecure their eſtate, or the moſt conſiderable part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This bout will only teach them the preſent failing, and how
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168902:20"/>to avoid it next. Now how ſoon they may get opportunity, God knowes, eſpecially when you provoke him, to ſuffer it, both againe and ſpeedily, <hi>Benhadad</hi> liv'd to repay <hi>Ahab,</hi> for letting him go, by a deaths wound at <hi>Ramoth Gilead.</hi> When God thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in his word againe, and again, be ſure a ſtorm is not very fat off. Howbeit bleſſed be God his Majeſty is innocent of this neglect (ſhould any be committed) having wholly left the matter to your pious diſcretion, and reſolutions.</p>
            <p n="95">95. By this means we ſhall have a young nurſery of Traytors enabled to give their native Country a blow (perhaps) when it is little aware of them, Children uſualy excuſing their fathers, unleſs their crimes be ſo laid open, and made notorious by puniſhment, as may make them hang their Creſts: Then they ſneake away, are aſhamed both of their name, and relation, endeavouring if poſſible, to obliterate out of memory, that they are deſcended from ſuch, and it will prove moſt true, and be conſtantly found by experience, that he who all his life ſtudies to defend ſuch vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanyes, will at length look upon them with liking, under the notion of heroick actions.</p>
            <p n="96">96. He who ſpares a malefactor (by the law of God and man unpardonable) had need of more than ordinary ſecurity, for his future good beheavour: it was the expreſſion, of a wiſe King who had pardoned a man (through great interceſſion for him) convicted of murther, and ſoone after was found guilty of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the like fact, which being told him he replyed, It is I have ſlaine this laſt man, for had juſtice been done on the murtherer at firſt, as God required according to the ſentence paft againſt him by the law, this laſt in probability had been alive. Murther Gentlemen, is prodigiouſly fertile, none guilty thereof; fail or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily of becoming apt and ready Schollars in Satans bloudy politicks, You know not what a muſter-roll of Crimſon ſins you invite Divine juſtice to place to your account for future, which will undoubtedly prove a treaſuring wrath againſt the day of wrath, and who knowes the time and terror of this vengeance.</p>
            <p n="97">97. Their acquitting from ſo black crimes, and bloudy guilt may perhaps moralize the fable of that farmer, who put a ſnake almoſt dead with cold, into his boſome to revive it, and was rewarded with a mortall bite, ſo ſoone as the warmth had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168902:21"/>it, it is is a proverb not to be neglected, Save a thiefe from the gallowes and thy ſelf ſhall not eſcape that deſtiny, if he can bring thee to it: The proverb is ſo true of none as of ſuch murtherers as theſe, who deſtroy not their natural fathers, but the father of their Country, ſubvert its lawes, and make the land groane with illegall oppreſſures, proſcricptions, and bloud-ſhed. Should God in judgement ſuffer them to have ſuch another day (as they would certainly hugge, and improve the opportunity, ſo) you and your poſterity ſhould firſt feel their requitall of this favour in procuring their pardon: they of all others would not ſuffer any to live, at leaſt to inhabit among them, who could ſay, I, or my father, ſaved them, or their fathers from deſerved execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for the like crimes before, and this now is the recompence.</p>
            <p n="98">98. And perhaps, although their children borne, long ſince, and men growne, before they became involved in ſuch guilt, may prove better than their fathers, yet from ſuch as hereafter may become fertile among them, what a peſtilent brood may come into the World, who by Gods law ſtand accurſed, and lie irremiſſibly under the bands of death, If a bird conſtantly lay ſuch an Egge as will produce a young one like her ſelfe, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in reaſon expect children to proceed from them, better than the fathers. The Jewes have a witty obſervation, nor perhaps un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true. That <hi>Agag</hi> King of <hi>Amal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> during thoſe two years which he abode with <hi>Saul,</hi> and verily thought the bitterneſs of death had been paſt, begat a Son from whom lineally came that <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Agagite,</hi> who in <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s time, had like to ſwallow up the whole Jewiſh Nation, in his unſatiable thirſt of revenge, becauſe one who ſate in the Kings gate, would not bow to him. The morall is very ſeaſonable, and ſadly to be thought upon, theſe bloud-guilty Traytors, who in juſtice are ſonnes of Death, whom God would have cut off in the midſt of their dayes, who are beyond all but fooliſh pity (which as the proverb truly hath it, ruines oftimes a City) may become the future fathers of ſuch a piſti lent brood, as may revenge Gods quarrell in the neglect of juſtice upon them, to the very fourth generation, of ſuch who are chiefly concerned in it: Nor is it unlikely, but our preſent <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> may be a branch of that bloudy Archrraytor, of his name, who long ago did ſuch miſchiefe in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:168902:21"/>
            <p n="99">99. Though their lives be ſpared, yet future credit and repute, its unlike they or their children ever will get in theſe Kingdomes, till the memory of them be buried in forgetfullneſs, So that whether they have Eſtates left, or no, their bare lives will ſerve to produce much and great miſchiefe; They have long been accuſtomed to vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies of a prodigious bigneſs; And ſcorn now to ſerve the Devill in ſneaking employments. Great Rogues, too lazy to dig; nor will beg, ſo long as <hi>England</hi> hath enemies. They are acquainted with all the petty inſtruments of villany three in Kingdoms, and if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſet them on work themſelves, can and will recommend their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes to forreigne Princes, that bear <hi>England</hi> little good will, what happineſs can we expect, but theſe will obſtruct, prove Remoras to, and retard? What miſchiefe hatched, but they will promote, and cheriſh, no truſting their good nature, who have diſcovered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves prodigies therein, no hoping for their repentance, who have been ſeared in their conſciences, with twelve years practiſe of the moſt heart-hardning villanies.</p>
            <p n="100">100. If any hopes ſhould appear in them of repentance, 'tis pity but it ſhould be promoted with execution of that deſerved doom, which God requires to be brought upon them, which to differ, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to acquit them from, is in effect to cauſe thoſe, who chiefly procure this indemnity for them, to injoy, neither life, or happineſs, longer than they can hinder it. They have been long acquainted with ſuch butcheries, and imperious uſurpation, ſo as to be courted, on that ſcore, by Kings, dreaded at home, ſeared abroad, and admired by nations far diſtant; this hath ſcrow'd up their minds to that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous pitch of impiety, that rather than live neglectedly, or in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, they will ſpare two pence at any time, although but maſters of a groat in all, to by a faggot, which may fire their native Country, then they will warme their hands and rejoyce at the flame.</p>
            <p n="101">101. Their long experience, although in an uſurped way, hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them dangerous perſons to be intereſted againſt their native country, &amp; the hopeleſneſs of their pardon, upon any future ſcore of rebellion, or Treaſon, would incourage any Prince to truſt them very far, who ſhall be ingaged againſt <hi>England.</hi> Theſe are great incarnate devills, every one of them is collective, a name of number, and there are in theſe Kingdomes a multitude of cloſe villians, of their own complexion, who are of inferior ranks and orders, yet miſchievous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in their kind, whom theſe formerly State-Angles, ſhining in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:168902:22"/>uſurped Glory, falling now to be State-Devills, will draw along with them, as <hi>Lucifer</hi> did his train after him, or as the Dragor in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalyps, drew the ſtarrs with his tail, theſe will ſtill, by reaſon of their cloſe agents, who will ingratiate themſelves as nigh the very Court, and grand Counſels of the Nation, as poſſible, learne, and betray your moſt choice and ſecret counſells, and reſolves to thoſe, where it will be little for the Nations advantage to have them known.</p>
            <p n="102">102. Believe it confidently, my Lords and Gentlemen, it will be thus, beſides the probability of the thing, you have his Warrant and threatning to aſſure you of it, whom you ſhall never taxe with breach of his word. No ſooner ſhall theſe be acquitted, but of your own number, one ſhall be <hi>Lenthall,</hi> another <hi>Haſlerigge,</hi> another <hi>Vane,</hi> a fourth <hi>Mildmay,</hi> a fift <hi>Whitlock,</hi> a ſixt <hi>Mounſon,</hi> a ſeventh <hi>Saint-Johns,</hi> and ſo on, in Gods eſteem and account, and who then ſo fit to execute his vengeance againſt you, but theſe very perſons, becauſe you neglected to do it upon them when God requir'd. And every man of you repreſenting a County, City, or Borough, what may be the lot of <hi>England,</hi> I tremble to think.</p>
            <p n="103">103. Thus my Lords and Gentlemen, I have given you ſome brief, but ſerious conſiderations, not but that I think your wiſedomes much more able to ventilate, and apprehend them, than I to ſuggeſt, but knowing your many imployments will hardly, if at all, admit moſt of you, to think on theſe things, out of the walls of your joynt deliberation, beſides, that ſo many interceſſors and friends are dayly made to you in their behalfe, as gives you little leiſure ſo profoundly to examine things, as one of far inferiour parts to the leaſt of you, may do, being without interruption. I ſhall in brief touch ſome things which may be objected in their behalf.</p>
            <p n="104">104. Thoſe who plead for them do it under the notion of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and for the moſt part uſe ſuch arguments as theſe, firſt Gods manner of bringing this about, without ſtroke, or bloud, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude this providence ſpeakes, that if any, yet as little bloud ought to be ſhed, as poſſibly may. Secondly his ſacred Majeſty of royall memory charging his ſon not to revenge his bloud. Thirdly the penitence of ſome, and expreſſion of contrary affections ſince, by ſignal duty. Fourthly, the pity they conceive ſo much bloud ſhould be ſhed in a time of Generall rejoycing. And Fiftly the ſafety of the Nation, which they imagine beſt ſecured by this mercy, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:168902:22"/>would be hazarded by the contrary ſeverity. Theſe are the frequent objections I meet withall, except ſome, which are brought in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of particular individuall perſons, which I ſhall not here take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p n="105">105. The firſt argument is well brought, but miſapplied, it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argues Gods intent to have them made examples, who therefore preſerved them, that they ſhould not fall otherwayes, which had things come to blows, might have prov'd likely enough; <hi>Achan</hi> who troubled the Camp, himſelf eſcaped, being reſerved by God to publick Juſtice, where God had declared a Nation devoted, and accurſed; <hi>Joſhuah</hi> uſed no leſſe ſeverity, though the victory hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without blood, than where men fell in battle; <hi>Jericho</hi> with all it's Inhabitants, Cattle, plunder and Houſes was utterly deſtroyed; although it fell at the ſound of Ramms Horns, and the ſhout of the Army, as well as <hi>Ai,</hi> where <hi>Joſhuah</hi> found a repulſe, Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is to be attended, concerning notorious Malefactors, as well though they be taken by unexpected ſurprizall, as if they had been ſubdued fighting: Yea, rather had they been in the field, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by a ſtrong Army, yet in fear of a greater force, they might have made terms for themſelves, which better than hazard both mens lives, and the cauſe it ſelf, might have been granted: but as God diſpoſed affairs, as they deſerve no pardon, ſo they can plead no Articles; They reſiſted to the laſt, nor yeilded till they were of all hands relinquiſhed and deſerted; yet even then, where force would do no good, they attempted Treachery; and wanted little of daſhing all our hopes, by ſowing diviſions in the Army.</p>
            <p n="106">106. The ſecond argument is a clear proof of that bleſſed Kings Piety, who with <hi>Steven</hi> could from his heart forgive his murtherers, but is no rule for his ſucceſſor, and Parliament to take him at his word: Though it be in villains power to murther their King, it is out of his power to pardon them, and though it argue his true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian piety, to beg their forgivneſs heartily from God, and to expreſs the ſame at the hour of death; yet there is a Law of God and man to be ſatisfied, for the fact, and it would be a cruell kindneſſe in the ſucceſſor, to muzzle the mouth of the Law, to indempnifie ſuch vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, whoſe crime, although God pardon and remit, as to future judgement, upon ſignall and true Repentance, yet if man upon any ſuch conſideration, acquit the temporall guilt, God will revenge it to purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:168902:23"/>
            <p n="107">107. To this may be added, that theſe wretches far exceeded what his Sacred Majeſty thought or could expect. He (pious King) hoped that thoſe, who were ſo deſperately cruel to him, would in compunction of heart, relent toward his Sonne, and feele ſuch a ſting in their conſcience, as might ingage them with ſo much greater zeal to ſtudy his Sonns good, and obſerve his juſt commands, by how much they were more cruelly barbarous to him: But alas! it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, otherwiſe, the Murtherers of the Father, rejected the Son, and continued his implacable enemies, with ſuch obſtinate impenitency, that nothing but a Divine miraculous courſe of proceeding did reſtore to us our Royall exile.</p>
            <p n="108">108. As to the third argument, I grant, that years of indiſcretion, a weak Judgement, importunacy of friends concerned, Sophiſticate arguments, eſpecially the Divine Oracles, pretending the thing to be of God; The Prophets propheſying this to be the way &amp; time of confounding the man of ſin, whoſe ſupporter they interpreted regal power to be falſe witneſſes affirming that his Majeſty had committed unapparel'd tyrannies, &amp; Solicitors thereupon, praying ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: But above all, Lawyers affirming ſuch proceedings to be juſt and regular, and the power commiſſionating them legall; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their giving peremptory authority to try the King: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines alſo (who pretended themſelves Caſuiſts) reſolving oaths no longer to bind, vows to be upon ſuch junctures enervated, when the King was Captivated, maintaining the power to be from, and in the people originally, with ſuch like Aphoriſmes, broached, and confidently defended by State and Pulpit-<hi>Boutefeus:</hi> I wonder not if many were ingaged in his Sacred Majeſties Tragedy where treaſon is only (indeed) their fault, and is by man pardonable, but the ſinn; of murder and perjury they before God ſtand acquitted off, being ſeduced by Divines and Lawyers, whoſe reverence, gravity, and reputed skill, learning and piety, was their ſhare, for whom what tongue can plead?</p>
            <p n="109">109. Where in conſcience the Honourable Lords or worthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons can excuſe the party concerned, to be thus deluded, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid but pardon may (as a true act of Grace) be granted, ſeverity involving them alſo: But upon this pretence to pardon Lawyers, as <hi>Lenthal, St. Johns, Cook, &amp;c.</hi> or men known of acute wits, as <hi>Haſlerigge, Vane, Martin, &amp;c.</hi> or thoſe who were his Majeſties ſervants, as <hi>Mildmay, Holland, Danvers, &amp;c.</hi> or indeed any, either
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:168902:23"/>Voters of the High Court of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Judges therein, who cannot make appear they were deluded, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no way be diſcovered, but either by their voluntary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Act afterward, or eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the contrary intereſt) and manging it with fidelity and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous proſecution, is to juſtifie the villany, and to draw the guilt upon the Nation inevitably.</p>
            <p n="110">110. The fourth argument is unſound and rotten, Our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, if it make us forget our miſery and duty, God will remind us of both with a vengeance. But further, if the number puniſhed be not greater than appears, moſt deſperate Malefactors, they are not too many to be exempted, as may appeare from theſe inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Rebellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft, how much more when aggravated with blood, yea, deſperate blood-guiltineſſe? Forty Witches at a time were counted no pitty to ſuffer, where perhaps all of them were not convicted of ten mens death, &amp; that only conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; Theſe are guilty of more than forty innocent mens lives, befides Royall blood valuable at ten thouſand, and thoſe ſlain in battle (to bring theſe murders about) a number not to be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, tis to be lamented, the Land affords ſo many villains, but no pitty to part with them,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices were many more, who only emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lared, ſlighted and contemned Authority, yet they, their Wives, Children, Servants, Tents, and all they had, went at once to perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the immediate hand of God himſelf, From whom ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was made by Divine command, upon penalty of partaking in their puniſhment. Certainly then, if theſe who deſtroyed and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled down all Authority that was Lawfull, and ſet up arbitrary tyranny inſtead thereof, dy an ordinary death, or in peace, thoſe who let them go, may fear leſt themſelves be cut off in the midſt of their dayes: to ſave theſe is a cruell friendſhip, and may prove worſe than an hereditary plague to their families, who are concerned in their impunity.</p>
            <p n="3">3, Thoſe who underwant puniſhment for <hi>Aarons</hi> Calf, were three thouſand, <hi>Ahabs</hi> Family, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zabels</hi> Prophets, and <hi>Balaams</hi> Prieſts many more, than our offenders. In a word, thoſe who pay for their obſtinacy in too long holding out a garriſon, Caſtle or with their lives, are of thirty times their number: The multitude of our ſlain in theſe Warres, which this prevarication of theirs hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168902:24"/>them guilty of, hath been a thouſand for one of them, No pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to be had of the number where a man cannot be excuſed with ſafety to the Nation. Prudent Generalls make no ſcruple to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute forty, for the ſafety of ten thouſand: as is apparent in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies, where oft the tenth man dies mercileſſe, for terror to the reſt, yet for theſe much may be pleaded, in defence, or at leaſt excuſe, for our murderers nothing,</p>
            <p n="111">111. The laſt argument is alſo grounded upon a cleare miſtake, the ſafety of this Nation is no more concerned in their pardon, than in ſuffering unquencht fire in the roofe, or Timberworke of an houſe; as may appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, if they could have checkt our hopes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>other'd theſe happy proceedings, or diverted counſells, we had never ſeen this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py day, nor do we injoy it now with their good will; their power is at preſent, bleſſed be God, leſs, though their malice, (as to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality) full as much, no fear of them now, if we be carefull, who could not hinder this our approaching proſperity then.</p>
            <p n="2">2, But Secondly, they are not out of hope ſtill, may they but ſcape with life, they yet have tricks to try, nor count the game quite loſt, while a gappe is ſtill open for fraud; If at laſt they can thrive by a cheat, they value not their preſent loſs at downright play. For this end they will diſoblige, (if poſſible) the old cavalty, inſtigate new favourites to diſguſting carriages, in a word, there ſhall be no ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, if they can diſquiet the State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But laſtly to echo againe what I oft ſaid before, I beſeech you take heed, leſt this Carnall device, to ſettle the Nation, provoke Gods Judgement to ſend ſuch a ſpirit of unſettledneſſe in theſe Kingdomes, (and that through their meanes) as may cauſe once more a ſword to be drawn in <hi>England,</hi> not to be ſheathed in many ages.</p>
            <p n="112">112. Thus my, Lords and Gentlemen, I have freely expreſſed my mind unto you, wherein if paſſion in the leaſt hath biaſſed me, I am much miſtaken; that I have plainly declared my conſcience, I crave humbly your pardon, not intending the edge or point of any thing, by me written ſhould ſo much as threaten you, for I hope from your Honours better things, and therefore whatever is expreſt here, preſuppoſeth that from your Honors, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, and my prayer is that God who is the wonderfull
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:168902:24"/>Counſellor, may direct and adviſe you, what may be for his Glory, his ſacred Majeſties Honour; Your peace, and comfort, and the whole Kingdomes welfare, and happineſs, So prayes.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed> Your Honours moſt obſervant, though unworthy Orator. GEORGE STARKEY.</signed>
               <dateline>St. Thomas Apoſtles
<date>June. 18. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
